so let's look at the upsides and
downsides of direct mapped cache --is
when we access the direct mapped cache
we need to look in only one place that
makes this cache fast if we need to look
in more than one place then we need to
wait for all of those to be read out we
don't need to figure out which one of
them if any has it and so on with a
direct mapped cache we just check in one
place if it's there we have it if it's
not there then it's a Miss so we can
very quickly determine whether we have a
hit or not so it's very good for hit
time it is also cheaper than more
complex caches because of it we only
need to do one comparison on every
access to the cache so we only need to
have one tagged comparator one valid bit
checker and so on and that also makes it
energy-efficient we only need to do one
tag comparison and one valid bit check
per access which spends less energy than
if we had to check more than one the
downsides of this cache are related to
the fact that the block must go in one
place to see why this is a problem
consider what happens if the processor
is frequently accesses blocks a and B
like this where both a and B map to the
same place in the cache when we access a
we will bring it to the cache when we
access B we need to put it in the same
place where a is currently so a needs to
be kicked out there is no choice about
what we kick out a has to go out when we
access a again B needs to be kicked out
and so on so the downside of this cache
is that it can have these conflicts
where particular blocks that we want to
use fight over the one spot in the cache
although the cache has plenty of other
spots that are underutilized what
conflicts do is they increase the miss
rate so we can have a cache that has a
fast hit time but suffers in the Miss
rate in return